So I thought we would we could talk
about craving
which is a central theme in Buddhism
and we've obviously spoken about it a
lot but
making sure that one is clear on that
can't be harmful even if you've been
doing it trying to practice for a while
just to make sure you're on the right
path >> and uh you know
>> and uh you know
one can understand what craving is in an
abstract manner
but sometimes uh you can get confused
like you know where is it actually you know
you know where is it actually you know
someone might be trying to find it
trying to actually see it trying to you
know dedicating themselves to get rid of
craving but where is it
>> how is it uh where can I find
And the you know just to just go over
the basic definition in the sutras
says the cause of suffering is craving
which makes for further being
accompanied by delight and lust
which rejoice rejoices here and there.
In other words, craving for sensual
pleasure, craving for being, craving for
non-being is the cause of suffering.
Yeah. Well, yeah. So, when it says uh
craving for um
craving for being, it does not refer to
like a metaphysical
future
in a in a sort of like a like a
uh being on the level of you know like
what what philosophies are trying to
decipher. what is a being and so on. It
well it includes that for sure but it
really refers to the quite a practical
way of so it says when the continuation
of being uh in other words it's just
like saying a continuation of your
isness the way you are the way your
tendencies are the way your pressures
are. So craving fuels the continuation
of that. Now of course that goes reaches
the metaphysics and reaches the the
whole like um um future and everything
else that would come as a result of
still being the way you are now.
So the craving that's that's that's
maintaining that is the craving towards
sensuality, sensual desires, sense
objects, craving towards being, craving
towards non-being. In other words,
craving towards um isness of certain
things, presence of certain things and
then craving for the absence of certain
other things. You don't want them to be.
But uh it's that craving that maintains
those those pathways and those domains.
So it's not like as I said, it's not
like a cravings for some abstract idea
of being and who I am and my identity.
It's a lot more palpable
um like a um maintenance of your
addictions, maintenance of your
dependencies, maintenance of your false uh securities
maintenance of your false uh securities
that you find in sense objects um
environment and so on. So that's what
the being is. So that's why you start um
uprooting that craving or restraining
that craving.
You're going to start feeling unsafe.
You're going to start feeling threatened
um anxious and so on because you are
undoing that which you are
and that's not going to be feel pleasant
initially at least until like you know
the right view is developed and so on
when then you start recognizing no
that's actually the true safety and true
liberation undoing of all being so if I
want to destroy craving
now >> uh I keep the precepts
>> uh I keep the precepts
center restraint and I sit down and I
want to destroy craving.
Where do I where do I Well, yes, you you
you you don't um you can't just
destroy craving as an object that you
can find and then just smash it. You can
unscrew it, put it that way. You can't
just just pull it out, get rid of it,
but you could
go around it in a correct manner that
would result in fundamental complete
unscrewing of that craving from your
experience, removal.
Um, so yeah, you could be thinking and
pondering about it all you want and
trying to understand and see and and and
abstract basically dwell in abstract
concepts of what craving is. But
practically that craving is that which
is manifested through your actions by
body, speech and mind. Through your
intentions they would be rooted in
craving. So whenever you act out you are
uh maintaining you are giving into the
craving you are maintaining the being.
Whenever you act by body by speech
mentally you are uh very much fueling
the dependencies the craving and and and
um and everything else that follows. So
you want to stop acting out of craving
sorry you want to uh uproot you want to
overcome the craving you want to remove
it from your experience you have to stop
engaging in any types of experience that
um are based on it that that stem from
it that are fueled by it and that fuel
it more in return.
So you in order to extinguish the fire
you have to remove its fuel. You have to
completely deplete it of anything
burnable. Anything that can serve and
susceptible to burn, you actually need
to abandon, remove, uh protect from
coming back into the fire and so on. And
that's how fire will eventually
completely go out. So how how do I know
that I'm actually doing that? You know
if I if I say okay well uh lust aversion
distraction >> that is uh those are based on craving
>> that is uh those are based on craving
>> to get rid of suffering. So I act out of
lust I act out aversion. I distract
myself. >> But uh when I stop doing that
>> But uh when I stop doing that
there's still tension.
>> Well yeah there is still fire. So, how
do I know that I'm uh actually
diminishing this fire of craving when
>> Well, initially you you probably won't
have a immediate reference point. So,
you need to use your intelligence and
intellect to arrive at the conclusion
that certain types of actions are more
likely to result in diminishing of
craving. It's not a really astrophysics
or or or neuroscience. You just need to
be honest with yourself. Sit down and
see which is more likely to increase the
thirst, desire, craving, pressure and
which is more likely to decrease it.
Which types of action, which courses of
of of my intentions that I follow would
would result in in accumulation,
um intensification of the fire and which
ones would result in diminishing of it.
>> But uh yeah, so it's not the fire that
you just started yesterday. It's a fire
that's been burning for who knows how
long and packed with fuel and burnable
materials. So once you stop adding more, yes,
So once you stop adding more, yes,
that's the obviously the first and the
necessary step. But then you also have
to now wait uh um make sure no new
things come into it and then wait
basically that things that are already
under fire burn.
That that has to be depleted to some
extent. How long do you have to wait? In
other words, how long you have to endure
that um internal fire that that's going to
um internal fire that that's going to
get amplified when you when you when you
when you stop adding more fuel to it.
Well, that depends on how big the fire
was, how passionate your actions were,
how much how infected they were with
greed, aversion, distraction,
hindrances. Um so it's not going to
disappear overnight. Uh but obviously if
you recognize that the key is to not add
new fuel to your existing fire to not uh
uh uh increase that then yeah patience
patient endurance ki as the sutas would
describe and that's pretty much the
training in virtue that's the sole
purpose of virtue it's not uh I mean
there are secondary benefits of virtue
in the sutras that the Buddha would talk
about but the real main benefit is
exactly like preventing any more
careless ignorance adding off the fuel
to the fire of craving, containing it
and then as the fire lessens the clearer
well the picture becomes clearer as to
what's really happening where re the
real issue is and then obviously with
the understanding it will be even easier
to not add more fuel. it will be even
easier to prevent the careless uh
accidental additions of fuel to that
craving because obviously you're
becoming more and more transparent and
you recognize those those risks those
dangers way before you even engage with
them. [snorts]
So having having faith in that basic
reasoning that's [snorts] you know if I
that's [snorts] you know if I
>> well having faith in the basic reasoning
just so that you can start doing it.
>> Yeah.
>> Just so that you can start training in
the precepts
>> but eventually
there the one can expect that that fire
will diminish and you will experience
that diminishment.
>> Yeah. It's just obviously what's going
to happen is um the fire might start
diminishing right away.
>> Yeah.
>> But the thing is when you're in the
fire, >> it burns equally. Doesn't matter how big
>> it burns equally. Doesn't matter how big
it is.
So you don't have a reference to how
much the old fire burnt more because
currently you're still burnt.
So that's why people would sometimes um
give up or lose faith because they
expect that external reference point to
show them how much fire has diminished.
So it it effectually is diminishing but
as I said all you have there and then
when the craving is present is the burn
of the craving.
So it just feels like that same craving
is always there. However,
if certain other things prompt you
uh like certain memories, certain
circumstances prompt you and and you get
reminded of how much worse it used to
be. That's when you realize oh actually
quite a lot of fire has diminished. Like
you encounter something that used to
make you act in a certain way and you
you couldn't control yourself and then
you stopped. You withdraw yourself from
it. you spend like you know decent
amount of time restraining
contemplating the right things
everything we talk about obviously when
the craving arises it still hurts like
the same way the pressure the desire but
then sometimes accidentally you just
stumble upon something you see hear
smell taste touch something that used to
you remember vividly the extent of
provocation that that would cause and
now you realize oh my mind didn't even
move or didn't even move the tenth of
what it used to move and Then you
recognize oh yeah from one point of view
presence of craving means yes there is
always going to be a degree of that burn
for as long as I'm not truly free which
is exactly what can motivate you to go
all the way to freedom but then on the
other hand you actually do get a glimpse
into the the the perspective that shows
you like oh actually there is a
difference now like in terms of the
intensity in terms of the the pressure
in terms of the ability to contain it
but uh yeah you cannot have that that
reference point equally
present all the time like some sort of
um lighthouse always showing you because
obviously you are within that craving.
That's why you have to keep reminding
yourself of the values maintaining the
context. You have to work your way out
from the inside. In other words,
>> and that's what the Buddha meant when he
said you can't um you can't measure your
progress uh like in the same sense that
uh a carpenter who uses his axe cannot
measure every day how much of his axe
handle has worn out but he knows that
through sticking through it I through
using the handle it is wearing out. I
can't say this much today and this much
it will wear tomorrow. By the time will
come when one day I'll pick it up and
realize, oh, my handle's gone. I need to
replace it.
>> And that's exactly the same with the
craving. You can get a sense that it's wearing
You can get a sense that it's wearing
out. You can get a even a recognition as
I said if something reminds you, but
overall you recognize that no, only when
it's gone I can know that it's gone.
Until then, I'm still doing the same
work. I'm still using it the same way.
[cough] And I was thinking of another like
And I was thinking of another like
you know you can think to yourself
uh I have been suffering I want to end
suffering my suffering
>> and in what ways have I tried to do that
so my whole life have I ever tried to
give up craving?
>> Yeah. Have I ever even attempted to go
in this direction?
>> I've I've thoroughly done it by the way.
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I've been doing it for
so long. Yeah,
>> for sure.
>> Have I even considered Have I even
considered Have I even attempted
genuinely to go in the other direction?
>> Because if this other direction which is
non- craving
>> is doesn't work. Well, there is then
what other direction is there?
>> Well, exactly. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Cuz I've gone the other way.
>> Yeah.
>> Now I'm try non- craving. That doesn't
work. Well, what what do I have to lose?
>> Training. Exactly. You know, I've got
the duka already.